So I'm going to speak about a problem that I have
إذا سوف أتحدث عن مشكلة لدي
and that's that I'm a philosopher.
و هي أنني فيلسوف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I go to a party and people ask me what do I do
عندما أذهب إلى حفل يسألني الناس ما هو عملي
and I say, "I'm a professor," their eyes glaze over.
فأقول أنا بروفيسور , تجد أعينهم تلمع
When I go to an academic cocktail party
عندما أذهب إلى حفل من خليط أكاديمي
and there are all the professors around, they ask me what field I'm in
و يكون هناك الجميع بروفيسرات , يسألونني في أي مجال أعمل
and I say, "philosophy" -- their eyes glaze over.
فأقول لهم فيلسوف .. تجد أعينهم تلمع
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
When I go to a philosopher's party
عندما أذهب إلى حفل فلاسفة
and they ask me what I work on and I say, "consciousness,"
و يسألونني ما هو عملي فأقول الإدراك
their eyes don't glaze over -- their lips curl into a snarl.
أعينهم لا تلمع... تلتوي شفاههم مزمجرة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I get hoots of derision and cackles and growls
وأحصل على صياح من السخرية والثرثرة والهدير
because they think, "That's impossible! You can't explain consciousness."
لأنهم يعتقدوا " أنه أمر مستحيل ! فأنت لا تستطيع تفسيرالإدراك
The very chutzpah of somebody thinking
الوقاحة الشديدة من اعتقاد البعض
that you could explain consciousness is just out of the question.
بأنك تستطيع تفسيرالإدراك هو فقط أمر غير معقول
My late, lamented friend Bob Nozick, a fine philosopher,
آخر صديق مرثي الفيلسوف المتميز بوب نوزيك
in one of his books, "Philosophical Explanations,"
في أحد كتبه " تفسيرات فلسفية
is commenting on the ethos of philosophy --
علق على روح الفلسفة
the way philosophers go about their business.
طريقة الفلاسفة القيام بأعمالهم
And he says, you know, "Philosophers love rational argument."
و قال أنت تعرف أن الفلاسفة يحبون الجدل المنطقي
And he says, "It seems as if the ideal argument
و قال يبدو و كأنه جدلا مثاليا
for most philosophers is you give your audience the premises
لمعظم الفلاسفة هو أنك تعطي جمهورك المقدمات الفلسفية
and then you give them the inferences and the conclusion,
ثم تعطيهم الإستنتاجات و النتيجة
and if they don't accept the conclusion, they die.
و إذا لم يقبلوا النتيجة , سيموتوا
Their heads explode." The idea is to have an argument
رؤوسهم ستنفجر. الفكرة هو أنك تحصل على جدال
that is so powerful that it knocks out your opponents.
هذا قوي بأنه سيقرع خصمنا
But in fact that doesn't change people's minds at all.
لكن في الواقع هذا لن يغير البتة عقول الناس
It's very hard to change people's minds
إنه من الصعب جدا أن نغير عقول الناس
about something like consciousness,
عن شيء ما مثل ا لإدراك
and I finally figured out the reason for that.
و تبين لي بشكل نهائي السبب في ذلك
The reason for that is that everybody's an expert on consciousness.
السبب لذلك أنه كل واحد يتوقع نفسه خبير في الإدراك
We heard the other day that everybody's got a strong opinion about video games.
سمعنا سابقا أن الكل لديه رأي قوي عن ألعاب الفيديو
They all have an idea for a video game, even if they're not experts.
الكل لديه رأي عن ألعاب الفيديو , حتى إذا لم يكونوا متخصصين
But they don't consider themselves experts on video games;
لكنهم لا يعتبرون أنفسهم متخصصين في ألعاب الفيديو
they've just got strong opinions.
هم فقط لديهم أراء قوية
I'm sure that people here who work on, say, climate change
أنا متأكد بأن الناس العاملون هنا , يقولون تغيير في البيئة
and global warming, or on the future of the Internet,
و الدفئ العالمي , أو في مستقبل الإنترنت
encounter people who have very strong opinions
نواجه الناس الذين لدهم أراء قوية
about what's going to happen next.
عن ماذا سيحدث لاحقا
But they probably don't think of these opinions as expertise.
لكنهم قد لا يعتقدوا بأن هذه الأراء كمتخصصين
They're just strongly held opinions.
هم فقط يحملون أراء
But with regard to consciousness, people seem to think,
لكن بالنسبة للإدراك , يبدو أن الناس تعتقد
each of us seems to think, "I am an expert.
كل واحد منا بأنه يعتقد " أنا متخصص
Simply by being conscious, I know all about this."
ببساطة بأن تكون مدرك , أنا أعرف كل شيء عن ذلك
And so, you tell them your theory and they say,
و هكذا , تقول لهم نظريتك و يقولوا
"No, no, that's not the way consciousness is!
لا , لا هذه ليست طريقة الإدراك
No, you've got it all wrong."
أنت حصلت عليها خطأ
And they say this with an amazing confidence.
و يقولوا ذلك بثقة مدهشة
And so what I'm going to try to do today
و لهذا ما سوف أقوم بتجربته اليوم
is to shake your confidence. Because I know the feeling --
هو بزعزعة ثقتكم . لأني أعرف الإحساس
I can feel it myself.
أستطيع أن أحس بها بنفسي
I want to shake your confidence that you know your own innermost minds --
أريد أن أزعزع ثقتكم بأنكم ستعرفون عقولكم المتوغلة بداخلكم
that you are, yourselves, authoritative about your own consciousness.
ذلك بأنكم لديكم الصلاحية عن إدراككم
That's the order of the day here.
هذا هو نظامنا اليوم هنا
Now, this nice picture shows a thought-balloon, a thought-bubble.
الآن , هذه الصورة الجميلة توضح بالون فكرة . فقاعة فكرة
I think everybody understands what that means.
أعتقد أن الكل يعرف معنى ذلك
That's supposed to exhibit the stream of consciousness.
من المفترض أن تعرض تدفق الإدراك
This is my favorite picture of consciousness that's ever been done.
هذه صورتي المفضلة عن الإدراك و التي من أفضل ما عمل
It's a Saul Steinberg of course -- it was a New Yorker cover.
إنها بالطبع سول ستينبرج .. كانت على غلاف مجلة نيويوركر
And this fellow here is looking at the painting by Braque.
و الشخص هنا ينظر إلى اللوحة الفنية للرسام براق
That reminds him of the word baroque, barrack, bark, poodle,
و هي تذكره بكلمة باروك , باراك , بارك , بودل
Suzanne R. -- he's off to the races.
ر سوزان -- خارج السباقات
There's a wonderful stream of consciousness here
هناك تدفق جميل من الإدراك
and if you follow it along, you learn a lot about this man.
و إذا تتبعتها , سوف تعرف الكثير عن هذا الرجل
What I particularly like about this picture, too,
ما هو بالتحديد الذي أحبه عن هذه الصورة أيضا
is that Steinberg has rendered the guy
هو أن ستينبرج وضع الشخص في المقدمة
in this sort of pointillist style.
بهذا النوع من نمط بوينتلست
Which reminds us, as Rod Brooks was saying yesterday:
و الذي يذكرنا بما قاله بالأمس رود بروك
what we are, what each of us is -- what you are, what I am --
ما نحن , ما كل واحد منا -- ما أنت , ما أنا
is approximately 100 trillion little cellular robots.
هو تقريبا 100 تريليون خلية روبوتات
That's what we're made of.
هذا ما نحن منه
No other ingredients at all. We're just made of cells, about 100 trillion of them.
لا محتويات أخرى أبدا. نحن من خلايا . تقريبا 100 تريليون خلية
Not a single one of those cells is conscious;
و لا واحد من هذه الخلايا مدرك
not a single one of those cells knows who you are, or cares.
و لا واحد من هذه الخلايا يعرف من أنت أو يهتم
Somehow, we have to explain
بطريقة ما علينا أن نفسر
how when you put together teams, armies, battalions
كيف عندما تضع فرق و جيوش و كتائب معا
of hundreds of millions of little robotic unconscious cells --
مكونة من مئات الملايين من خلايا روبوتية صغيرة غير واعية
not so different really from a bacterium, each one of them --
ليست حقا مختلفة عن البكتريا , في كل واحدة منهم
the result is this. I mean, just look at it.
النتيجة هي هذه. أعني فقط أنظر إليها
The content -- there's color, there's ideas, there's memories,
المحتوى -- هناك لون , هناك أفكار , هناك ذكريات
there's history. And somehow all that content of consciousness
هناك تاريخ . و بطريقة ما كل ذلك المحتوى من الإدراك
is accomplished by the busy activity of those hoards of neurons.
يتم انجازه بواسطة الأنشطة المنشغلة من النيرونات المكنوزة
How is that possible? Many people just think it isn't possible at all.
كيف يمكن ذلك ؟ يعتقد كثير من الناس أن ذلك غير ممكن أبدا
They think, "No, there can't be any
يعتقدوا , " أنه لا يمكن أن يكون هناك أي
sort of naturalistic explanation of consciousness."
نوع من التفسير الطبيعي للإدراك
This is a lovely book by a friend of mine named Lee Siegel,
هذا كتاب جميل لصديق لي اسمه " ليي سيقل
who's a professor of religion, actually, at the University of Hawaii,
و هو بروفيسور في الدين , في جامعة هاواي
and he's an expert magician, and an expert
و هو متخصص في السحر, و متخصص
on the street magic of India, which is what this book is about,
في سحر الشوارع في الهند , و هو ما يتحدث عنه في الكتاب
"Net of Magic."
" شبكة ا لسحر
And there's a passage in it which I would love to share with you.
و يوجد فيه فقرة أحب أن أشاركك إياها
It speaks so eloquently to the problem.
إنها تتحدث ببلاغة عن المشكلة
"'I'm writing a book on magic,' I explain, and I'm asked, 'Real magic?'
"أنا أكتب كتابا عن تفسير السحر, و سئلت عن السحر الحقيقي ؟
By 'real magic,' people mean miracles,
ما يقصده الناس بالسحر الحقيقي هو المعجزات
thaumaturgical acts, and supernatural powers.
تصرفات صانع المعجزات , و القوى الخارقة
'No,' I answer. 'Conjuring tricks, not real magic.'
لا . أنا أجيب . الشعوذة ليست سحر حقيقي
'Real magic,' in other words, refers to the magic that is not real;
بمعنى آخر السحر الحقيقي يرجع للسحر الذي هو غير حقيقي
while the magic that is real, that can actually be done, is not real magic."
بينما السحر هو حقيقي ,و يمكن في الواقع فعله ,فهو ليس سحر حقيقي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now, that's the way a lot of people feel about consciousness.
الآن , هذه هي الطريقة التي يشعر بها الناس تجاه الإدراك
Real consciousness is not a bag of tricks.
الإدراك الحقيقي هو ليست حقيبة من الخدع
If you're going to explain this as a bag of tricks,
إذا كنت ستفسر هذا كحقيبة من الخدع
then it's not real consciousness, whatever it is.
ثم هو ليس إدراك حقيقي , مهما كان ذلك
And, as Marvin said, and as other people have said,
وكما قالت مارفين , و كما قال الآخرون
"Consciousness is a bag of tricks."
الإدراك هو حقيبة من الخدع
This means that a lot of people are just left completely dissatisfied
هذا يعني أن الكثير من الناس فقط تركوا غير راضين تماما
and incredulous when I attempt to explain consciousness.
و بميولي للشك عندما أحاول تفسير الإدراك
So this is the problem. So I have to
إذا هذه هي ا لمشكلة . لذا يجب أن أحاول
do a little bit of the sort of work
أن أقوم بعمل شيئا ما
that a lot of you won't like,
و لا يحبه الكثير منكم
for the same reason that you don't like to see
لمثل هذا السبب سوف لن تحب أن ترى
a magic trick explained to you.
خدعة السحر تفسر لك
How many of you here, if somebody -- some smart aleck --
كم واحد منكم هنا , إذا شخصا ما -- استعراضي بارع
starts telling you how a particular magic trick is done,
يبدأ يقول لكم خاصة كيف يتم عمل خدع السحر
you sort of want to block your ears and say, "No, no, I don't want to know!
أنت نوعا ما تريد إغلاق أذنيك و تقول , لا , لا أنا لا أحب أن أعرف
Don't take the thrill of it away. I'd rather be mystified.
لا تنزع عامل التشويق منها , أنا أفضل أن أكون مندهشا بشدة
Don't tell me the answer."
لا تقل لي الإجابة
A lot of people feel that way about consciousness, I've discovered.
اكتشفت أن كثيرا من الناس يشعر بهذه الطريقة حول الإدراك
And I'm sorry if I impose some clarity, some understanding on you.
و أنا متأسف إذا أضفت بعض التوضيح , و أفهتمك البعض
You'd better leave now if you don't want to know some of these tricks.
يفضل أن تغادر الآن إذا لم تحب أن تتعرف على بعض هذه الخدع
But I'm not going to explain it all to you.
لكنني لن أفسرها لك كلها
I'm going to do what philosophers do.
أنا سوف أفعل ما يفعله الفلاسفة
Here's how a philosopher explains the sawing-the-lady-in-half trick.
إليك كيف يشرح الفيلسوف خدعة نشر السيدة بالمنشار
You know the sawing-the-lady-in-half trick?
هل تعرف خدعة نشر السيدة بالمنشار ؟
The philosopher says, "I'm going to explain to you how that's done.
يقول الفيلسوف " أنا سأقوم بشرحها لك كيف تتم
You see, the magician doesn't really saw the lady in half."
أنت ترى , أن الساحر في الواقع لا يرى السيدة مقطوعة بالنصف
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"He merely makes you think that he does."
" ببساطة هنا أنت تعتقد حتما أنه يراها كذلك
And you say, "Yes, and how does he do that?"
و تقول " نعم , و كيف هو يفعل ذلك
He says, "Oh, that's not my department, I'm sorry."
يقول , " أوه , أنا آسف لأنه ليس من تخصصي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So now I'm going to illustrate how philosophers explain consciousness.
إذا الآن سوف أوضح لكم كيف الفلاسفة يفسروا الإدراك
But I'm going to try to also show you
لكن سوف أحاول أيضا أن أريكم
that consciousness isn't quite as marvelous --
أن الإدراك ليس تماما مثل الإعجاز
your own consciousness isn't quite as wonderful --
إدراكك ليس تماما رائع
as you may have thought it is.
و كأنك كما فكرت به
This is something, by the way, that Lee Siegel talks about in his book.
بالمناسبة هذا شيء ما تكلم عنه " ليي سيقل " في كتابه
He marvels at how he'll do a magic show, and afterwards
أعجز في كيفية قيامه بعروض السحر , و من ثم
people will swear they saw him do X, Y, and Z. He never did those things.
سيقول الناس أحلف أنني رأيته يفعل كيت و كيت . هو لم يفعل ذلك البتة
He didn't even try to do those things.
و حتى أنه لم يحاول فعل ذلك
People's memories inflate what they think they saw.
الناس يضخموا من ذكريات ما يعتقدون أنهم قد رأوا
And the same is true of consciousness.
و بالمثل هذا صحيح للإدراك
Now, let's see if this will work. All right. Let's just watch this.
الآن , دعنا نرى إن كان هذا سيعمل . حسنا . دعنا نراقب هذا
Watch it carefully.
راقبه جيدا
I'm working with a young computer-animator documentarian
أنا أعمل مع شاب في توثيق رسوم الكمبويتر ا لمتحركة
named Nick Deamer, and this is a little demo that he's done for me,
اسمه " نك ديمر " و هذا عرض بسيط أنجزه لي
part of a larger project some of you may be interested in.
من مشروع كبير قد يهم البعض منكم
We're looking for a backer.
نحن نبحث عن مساعد
It's a feature-length documentary on consciousness.
إنه فيلم وثائقي مميزوطويل عن الإدراك
OK, now, you all saw what changed, right?
حسنا . الآن أنت ترى ما الذي تغير . صحيح ؟
How many of you noticed that every one of those squares changed color?
كم شخص منكم لاحظ أن كل واحد من هذه المربعات تغيرلونه ؟
Every one. I'll just show you by running it again.
الكل . سوف أريكم ثانية بإعادة تشغيله
Even when you know that they're all going to change color,
حتى عندما تعرف أن اللون سيتغير
it's very hard to notice. You have to really concentrate
صعب ملاحظة ذلك . في الواقع يجب أن تركز
to pick up any of the changes at all.
لتعرف ما التغييرات التي حصلت
Now, this is an example -- one of many --
الآن , هذا مثال -- من بعض الأمثلة
of a phenomenon that's now being studied quite a bit.
لظاهرة يتم دراستها بشكل لا بأس به
It's one that I predicted in the last page or two of my
إنها واحدة مما تنبأت به في آخر صفحة أو اثنين من
1991 book, "Consciousness Explained,"
كتابي 1991 , " تفسير الإدراك
where I said if you did experiments of this sort,
و فيه قلت إذا عملت مثل هذا النوع من التجارب
you'd find that people were unable to pick up really large changes.
سوف تجد أن الناس غير قادرين على التعرف على التغييرات الكبيرة
If there's time at the end,
إذا لدينا وقت في النهاية
I'll show you the much more dramatic case.
سوف أريكم حالة أكثر إثارة
Now, how can it be that there are all those changes going on,
الآن , كيف يمكن لكل هذه التغييرات أن تستمر
and that we're not aware of them?
و نحن لا ندركها ؟
Well, earlier today, Jeff Hawkins mentioned the way your eye saccades,
حسنا , اليوم باكرا " جيف هوكنس " تكلم عن حركة عينك السريعة
the way your eye moves around three or four times a second.
طريقة حركة عينيك من ثلاثة إلى أربعة مرات في الثانية
He didn't mention the speed. Your eye is constantly in motion,
لم يذكر السرعة . عينك بإستمرار في حركة
moving around, looking at eyes, noses, elbows,
تتحرك , تنظر إلى العيون , الأنف, المرفقين
looking at interesting things in the world.
تنظر إلى الأشياء المهمة في ا لعالم
And where your eye isn't looking,
و أين عينك لا تنظر
you're remarkably impoverished in your vision.
بشكل ملحوظ أنت لا تتحكم في بصرك
That's because the foveal part of your eye,
هذا بسبب الجزء المنخفض من عينك
which is the high-resolution part,
و هو الجزء العالي الدقة
is only about the size of your thumbnail held at arms length.
و هو تقريبا بحجم ظفر الإبهام مقارنة بطول ذراعيك
That's the detail part.
هذا الجزء المفصل
It doesn't seem that way, does it?
لا يبدو بهذه ا لطريقة . هل يبدو كذلك ؟
It doesn't seem that way, but that's the way it is.
لا يبدو بهذه الطريقة , لكن هذه هي الطريقة
You're getting in a lot less information than you think.
أنت تحصل على معلومات أقل بكثير مما تعتقد
Here's a completely different effect. This is a painting by Bellotto.
إليك تأثير مختلف تماما . هذه لوحة فنية رسمها " بيلوتو
It's in the museum in North Carolina.
إنه متحف في ولاية كارولينا الشمالية
Bellotto was a student of Canaletto's.
بيلوتو كان طالبا في " كاناليتو
And I love paintings like that --
و أنا أحب مثل هذه اللوحة الفنية
the painting is actually about as big as it is right here.
في الواقع حجم اللوحة تماما كما هو هنا
And I love Canalettos, because Canaletto has this fantastic detail,
و أنا أحب الكاناليتو لأن كاناليتو لديه هذا التفصيل الرائع
and you can get right up
و يمكنك الحصول عليها
and see all the details on the painting.
و ترى كل التفاصيل في اللوحة
And I started across the hall in North Carolina,
وبدأت في انحاء القاعة في ولاية كارولينا الشمالية
because I thought it was probably a Canaletto,
لأنني كنت أعتقد أنها ربما تكون كاناليتو
and would have all that in detail.
و سوف أحصل على كل ذلك بالتفصيل
And I noticed that on the bridge there, there's a lot of people --
و لاحظت فوق الجسر هناك أشخاص كثيرين
you can just barely see them walking across the bridge.
بالكاد تستطيع أن تراهم يمشون عبر الجسر
And I thought as I got closer
و أعتقدت عندما أقتربت أكثر
I would be able to see all the detail of most people,
أنني سأتمكن من رؤية كل تفاصيل الأشخاص
see their clothes, and so forth.
أرى ملابسهم و هكذا
And as I got closer and closer, I actually screamed.
و عندما أقتربت أكثر و أكثر , في الواقع صرخت
I yelled out because when I got closer,
صحت لأنني عندما أقتربت أكثر
I found the detail wasn't there at all.
لم أجد التفاصيل هناك أبدا
There were just little artfully placed blobs of paint.
كان هناك فقط قليل من النقاط موضوعة بشكل فني على اللوحة
And as I walked towards the picture,
و عندما مشيت بإتجاه الصورة
I was expecting detail that wasn't there.
توقعت تفاصيل لم تكن هناك
The artist had very cleverly suggested people and clothes
الرسام بشكل ذكي وضع ايحاءات الأشخاص و الملابس
and wagons and all sorts of things,
و العربات و كل أنواع الأشياء
and my brain had taken the suggestion.
و عقلي استلم تلك الإيحاءات
You're familiar with a more recent technology, which is -- There,
أنت على دراية بأكثر تكنولوجيا حديثة
you can get a better view of the blobs.
تستطيع أن تحصل على منظر أفضل للنقاط
See, when you get close
أنظر عندما تقترب أكثر
they're really just blobs of paint.
فعلا إنها فقط نقاط من الطلاء
You will have seen something like this -- this is the reverse effect.
سوف ترى شيئا مثل هذا -- هذا حركة عكسية
I'll just give that to you one more time.
سوف أعيد هذا فقط مرة أخرى
Now, what does your brain do when it takes the suggestion?
الآن , ماذا يعمل دماغك عندما يأخذ الإيحاء ؟
When an artful blob of paint or two, by an artist,
نقطة مخادعة من الطلاء أو نقطتين
suggests a person -- say, one of
توحي بشخص -- يقول واحد من
Marvin Minsky's little society of mind --
قليلا من المجمتع العقلي لـ " مارفين مينسكي
do they send little painters out to fill in all the details in your brain somewhere?
هل يرسلون طلاءات قليلة لملئ كل التفاصيل في مكان ما من دماغك ؟
I don't think so. Not a chance. But then, how on Earth is it done?
لا أعتقد ذلك .ليس صدفة.لكن بعد ذلك كيف فعلها على أرض الواقع ؟
Well, remember the philosopher's explanation of the lady?
حسنا , تذكر تفسير الفيلسوف لموضوع السيدة ؟
It's the same thing.
إنه نفس الشيئ
The brain just makes you think that it's got the detail there.
الدماغ يجعلك تعتقد بأنك حصلت على التفاصيل هناك
You think the detail's there, but it isn't there.
تعتقد أن التفاصيل هناك , لكنها ليست هناك
The brain isn't actually putting the detail in your head at all.
الدماغ في الواقع لم يضع أي تفاصيل بتاتا في رأسك
It's just making you expect the detail.
هو فقط جعلك تتوقع التفاصيل
Let's just do this experiment very quickly.
دعنا نقوم بهذه التجربة على عجالة
Is the shape on the left the same as the shape on the right, rotated?
هل الشكل في اليسار يدور مثل الشكل الذي في اليمين ؟
Yes.
نعم
How many of you did it by rotating the one on the left
كم واحد منكم فعلها بتدوير الواحدة التي في اليسار
in your mind's eye, to see if it matched up with the one on the right?
في عين دماغك , لترى إذا كانت تتوافق مع التي في اليمين
How many of you rotated the one on the right? OK.
كم واحد منكم فعلها بتدوير الواحدة التي في ا ليمين ؟ حسنا
How do you know that's what you did?
كيف تعرف أنك فعلت هذه ؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There's in fact been a very interesting debate
في الحقيقة هناك جدل مثير للإهتمام
raging for over 20 years in cognitive science --
متأجج منذ 20 سنة في العلوم المعرفية
various experiments started by Roger Shepherd,
تجارب عديدة بدأها " روجر شيفيرد
who measured the angular velocity of rotation of mental images.
الذي قاس سرعة تدوير الزاوية للصور الذهنية
Yes, it's possible to do that.
نعم , من الممكن فعل ذلك
But the details of the process are still in significant controversy.
لكن تفاصيل العملية ما زالت تحت جدل كبير
And if you read that literature, one of the things
و إذا قرأت تلك المقالة , واحدة من الأشياء
that you really have to come to terms with is
أنت فعلا يجب أن تتوصل إلى
even when you're the subject in the experiment, you don't know.
حتى و أنت معرض للتجربة سوف لن تعرف ذلك
You don't know how you do it.
لا تعرف كيف تفعلها
You just know that you have certain beliefs.
أنت تعرف فقط بأنه لديك معتقدات
And they come in a certain order, at a certain time.
و تأتي في ترتيب معين و في وقت معين
And what explains the fact that that's what you think?
و ما يفسر الحقيقة هو ما تفكر فيه
Well, that's where you have to go backstage and ask the magician.
حسنا , هناك يجب أن تذهب خلف الكواليس و تسأل الساحر
This is a figure that I love: Bradley, Petrie, and Dumais.
هذا الشكل الذي أحبه : برادلي و بيتري و دوماي
You may think that I've cheated,
قد تعتقد بأنني قد غششت
that I've put a little whiter-than-white boundary there.
بأنني قد وضعت بياضا أقل من بياض الحدود هناك
How many of you see that sort of boundary,
كم منكم يرى ذلك النوع من الحدود
with the Necker cube floating in front of the circles?
مع مكعب نيكر الذي يعوم أمام الدوائر ؟
Can you see it?
هل تستطيع أن تراه ؟
Well, you know, in effect, the boundary's really there, in a certain sense.
حسنا , أنت تعرف في الواقع بأن الحدود هناك فعلا بأسلوب مميز
Your brain is actually computing that boundary,
دماغك فعلا يحسب الحدود
the boundary that goes right there.
الحدود التي هي هناك تماما
But now, notice there are two ways of seeing the cube, right?
لكن الآن لاحظ أنه يوجد طريقتين لرؤية المكعب . هل هذا صحيح ؟
It's a Necker cube.
إنه مكعب نيكر
Everybody can see the two ways of seeing the cube? OK.
الكل يستطيع أن يرى الطريقتين لرؤية المكعب ؟ صحيح
Can you see the four ways of seeing the cube?
هل بإمكانك أن ترى الطرق الأربعة لرؤية المكعب ؟
Because there's another way of seeing it.
لأنه يوجد طريقة أخرى لرؤيته
If you're seeing it as a cube floating in front of some circles,
إذا كنت تراه كمكعب عائم أمام بعض الدوائر
some black circles, there's another way of seeing it.
بعض الدوائر السوداء , هناك طريقة أخرى لرؤيتها
As a cube, on a black background,
كمكعب , على خلفية سوداء
as seen through a piece of Swiss cheese.
كما يرى من خلال قطعة من الجبن السويسري
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Can you get it? How many of you can't get it? That'll help.
هل وجدتها ؟ كم واحد منكم لم يجدها ؟ هذا سيساعد
Now you can get it. These are two very different phenomena.
الآن تستطيع أن تجدها . هذان ظاهرتين مختلفتين جدا
When you see the cube one way, behind the screen,
عندما ترى المكعب بطريقة واحدة من خلف الشاشة
those boundaries go away.
هذه الحدود ستختفي
But there's still a sort of filling in, as we can tell if we look at this.
لكن لايزال نوع من التعبئة , كما يمكننا قول ذلك إذا نظرنا إلى هذه
We don't have any trouble seeing the cube, but where does the color change?
ليس لدينا مشكلة في رؤية المكعب , و لكن أين تغير اللون ؟
Does your brain have to send little painters in there?
هل يرسل دماغك قليلا من الطلاءات إلى هناك ؟
The purple-painters and the green-painters
الطلاءات البنفسجية و الطلاءات الخضراء
fight over who's going to paint that bit behind the curtain? No.
قاتل بشدة , من سيطلى هذا الجزء خلف الستارة ؟ لا
Your brain just lets it go. The brain doesn't need to fill that in.
دماغك سيجعلها تستمر . لا يحتاج الدماغ أن يملأها
When I first started talking about
عندما بدأت أتكلم أولا عن
the Bradley, Petrie, Dumais example that you just saw --
مثال برادلي و بيتري و دوماي الذي رأيته الآن
I'll go back to it, this one --
سوف أعود إليه , هذا هو
I said that there was no filling-in behind there.
أنا قلت لا يوجد أي تعبئة خلف ذلك
And I supposed that that was just a flat truth, always true.
و المفترض أن ذلك كان سطح حقيقي , دائما حقيقي
But Rob Van Lier has recently shown that it isn't.
لكن " بوب فان لير " أثبت مؤخرا أنها ليست كذلك
Now, if you think you see some pale yellow --
الآن , إذا كنت تعتقد أنك ترى الأصفر الباهت
I'll run this a few more times.
سوف أشغل هذا بضع مرات
Look in the gray areas,
أنظر في المساحة الرمادية
and see if you seem to see something sort of shadowy moving in there --
و انظر إن كنت تستطيع أن ترى شيئا ما كالظل يتحرك هناك في الداخل
yeah, it's amazing. There's nothing there. It's no trick.
نعم . إنه مدهش . لا يوجد شيئ هناك . إنها ليست خدعة
["Failure to Detect Changes in Scenes" slide]
هذا عمل " رون رينسنك , الذي كان لدرجة ما
This is Ron Rensink's work, which was in some degree
ملهما بإقتراحه تماما في آخر كتابه
inspired by that suggestion right at the end of the book.
دعني أوقف هذه لثواني إن استطعت
Let me just pause this for a second if I can.
هذه تغيير العمى
This is change-blindness.
ما ستراه هو صورتين
What you're going to see is two pictures,
واحدة مختلفة عن الأخرى
one of which is slightly different from the other.
ترى هنا السقف الأحمر و السقف الرمادي
You see here the red roof and the gray roof,
و بينهما سوف يكون هناك قناع
and in between them there will be a mask,
و هو تماما شاشة فارغة , لحوالي ربع ثانية
which is just a blank screen, for about a quarter of a second.
إذا سوف ترى الصورة الأولى , ثم القناع
So you'll see the first picture, then a mask,
ثم الصورة الثانية , ثم القناع
then the second picture, then a mask.
و هكذا ستستمر , و عملك هو المتابعة
And this will just continue, and your job as the subject
هو أن تضغط على الإزرار عندما ترى التغيير
is to press the button when you see the change.
إذا , تظهر الصورة الأساسية لمدة 240 ميللي ثانية . فراغ
So, show the original picture for 240 milliseconds. Blank.
تظهر الصورة التالية لمدة 240 ميللي ثانية . فراغ
Show the next picture for 240 milliseconds. Blank.
و استمر كذلك , حتى يضغط المتابع على الأزرار و يقول
And keep going, until the subject presses the button, saying,
رأيت التغيير
"I see the change."
إذا الآن سوف نكون المتابعين في التجربة
So now we're going to be subjects in the experiment.
سوف نبدأ بالتدرج . بعض الأمثلة
We're going to start easy. Some examples.
لا مشكلة هناك
No trouble there.
هل يستطيع الجميع أن يرى ؟ حسنا
Can everybody see? All right.
في الواقع , المتابعين لـ" رينسنك " أخذوا فقط وقتا أكثر بقليل
Indeed, Rensink's subjects took only a little bit more
من الثانية للضغط على الإزرار
than a second to press the button.
هل تستطيع رؤية تلك ؟
Can you see that one?
2.9 ثانية
2.9 seconds.
كم واحد لم يراها بعد ؟
How many don't see it still?
ماذا على سقف ذلك المخزن ؟
What's on the roof of that barn?
(ضحك)
(Laughter)
إنه سهل
It's easy.
هل هذا جسر أو سقالة
Is it a bridge or a dock?
هناك عدد آخر قليل أكثر أثارة , ثم سأنتهي
There are a few more really dramatic ones, and then I'll close.
أريدكم أن تروا القليل و خاصة تلك المتضاربة
I want you to see a few that are particularly striking.
هذه لأنها كبيرة و مع ذلك من الصعب رؤيتها
This one because it's so large and yet it's pretty hard to see.
هل تستطيع أن تراها ؟
Can you see it?
الجمهور : نعم
Audience: Yes.
أنظر إلى الظلال يرجع للخلف و الأمام ؟ كبيرة نوعا ما
Dan Dennett: See the shadows going back and forth? Pretty big.
إذا 15 و نصف ثانية هو متوسط الوقت
So 15.5 seconds is the median time
للمتابعين في تجربته هناك
for subjects in his experiment there.
أنا أحب هذه . سوف أنهي بهذه
I love this one. I'll end with this one,
لأنها فقط واضحة و شيء مهم
just because it's such an obvious and important thing.
كم منكم لايزال لم يراها ؟كم منكم لم يزال لم يراها ؟
How many still don't see it? How many still don't see it?
كم محرك على جناح البوينج ؟
How many engines on the wing of that Boeing?
(ضحك)
(Laughter)
هنا تماما في منتصف الصورة
Right in the middle of the picture!
شكرا جزيلا لإهتمامكم
Thanks very much for your attention.
ما أريد أن أريكم هو أن العلماء
What I wanted to show you is that scientists,
يستخدموا طريقة الشخص الثالث من الخارج
using their from-the-outside, third-person methods,
بأن يخبرك أشياء عن إدراكك
can tell you things about your own consciousness
لم تكن تحلم به
that you would never dream of,
و في الواقع أنت لست المخول
and that, in fact, you're not the authority
لإدراكك الخاص إذا كنت تعتقد ذلك
on your own consciousness that you think you are.
و نحن فعلا عملنا تقدما كثيرا
And we're really making a lot of progress
بإحضار نظرية العقل
on coming up with a theory of mind.
جيف هوكنز هذا الصباح كان يشرح محاولته
Jeff Hawkins, this morning, was describing his attempt
بالحصول على نظرية , نظرية كبيرة جيدة , في علم الأعصاب
to get theory, and a good, big theory, into the neuroscience.
و هو على حق . إنها مشكلة
And he's right. This is a problem.
ذات مرة مدرسة هارفارد الطبية -- عندما كنت محاضرا
Harvard Medical School once -- I was at a talk --
رئيس المختبر قال " في مختبرنا , لدينا مقولة
director of the lab said, "In our lab, we have a saying.
إذا عملنا في خلية عصبية واحدة , نسميه علم الأعصاب
If you work on one neuron, that's neuroscience.
إذا عملنا في خلييتين عصبيتين , نسميه علم النفس
If you work on two neurons, that's psychology."
(ضحك)
(Laughter)
علينا أن نحصل على نظريات أكثر ,و ممكن أن تأتي من أعلى إلى أسفل
We have to have more theory, and it can come as much from the top down.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
Thank you very much.
(تصفيق)